# Heritage Consultant and Archaeologist

Chris Uchiyama is a Heritage Consultant and Archaeologist with more than a decade of experience working on heritage aspects of planning and development projects. Ms. Uchiyama received her M.A. in Heritage Conservation from the Carleton University School of Canadian Studies in 2012. She has written, as lead author or co-author, more than 100 technical cultural heritage reports, including: archaeological licence reports; collections management materials; inventories; cultural heritage evaluation reports; and heritage impact assessments. She has worked on development projects ranging from individual properties to large-scale energy and resource extraction projects. She has a great deal of experience working with multi-disciplinary teams, providing advice on compliance with heritage policies and legislation, on development and planning proposals and has been involved in development proposals at all levels of government.

## **EDUCATION**

M.A., Heritage Conservation, Carleton University, Ottawa, Ontario, 2012

B.A. (Honours), Classical Archaeology, Wilfrid Laurier University, Waterloo, Ontario, 2003

## PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

Stone Preservation: Merging Traditional Approaches with Modern Technology, Association for Preservation Technology International Webinar, 2013

Aboriginal Worldviews, Coursera, 2013

Planning Primer I, Planning Primer II, and Heritage Planning Elective, City of Ottawa, 2011 and 2013

Heritage Obligations under the Treasury Board Policy on Management of Real Property, Federal Heritage Buildings Review Office, 2011

World Heritage Centre Intern, 34th Session of the UNESCO World Heritage Committee, Brasilia, Brazil, 2010 as Masters Candidate

#### PROFESSIONAL ASSOCIATIONS

Heritage Canada the National Trust, Member

Ontario Archaeological Society, Member

Canadian Archaeological Association, Member

Ontario Association of Professional Archaeologists, Member

Association for Preservation Technology International, Member of the Education and Research focus group of the Technical Committee on Sustainable Preservation

## **WORK EXPERIENCE**

Chris Uchiyama Heritage, Sole Proprietor, Heritage Consultant and Archaeologist 2014present | Letourneau Heritage Consulting Inc., Associate 2015-present | Stantec Consulting, Heritage Consultant and Archaeologist 2010-2013 | Jacques Whitford, Archaeologist and Heritage Consultant 2008-2010 | Jacques Whitford, Archaeologist 2003-2005

## PROJECT EXPERIENCE

2015

Heritage Impact Assessment, Millbrook Dam Reconstruction, Millbrook, Ontario – Undertook historical research, documentation, and evaluation of the cultural heritage value or interest (under O.Reg.9/06) of a cultural heritage landscape comprising an historic mill, millpond and dam. Assessed potential project-related impacts on heritage attributes and surrounding cultural heritage resources and recommended mitigation measures to lessen or avoid impacts. The HIA was undertaken as part of a Proponent-Driven Environmental Assessment being prepared by the Otonabee Region Conservation Authority.

Cultural Heritage Evaluation Report, Charleston Lake Provincial Park: Green Island, Park Boathouse, Junior Ranger's Cabin, and Park Warden's Cabin – Undertook historical research, documentation, and evaluation of the regional and provincial cultural heritage value or interest (under O.Reg.9/06 and O.Reg.10/06) of four discreet sites in the Charleston Lake Provincial Park. Identified heritage attributes and provided a series of alternatives and recommendations for the future use or decommissioning of each of the four sites.

# Christienne Uchiyama, M.A.

Heritage Consultant and Archaeologist

Cultural Heritage Impact Assessment for 14640 Woodbine Avenue, Whitchurch-Stouffville, Ontario – Undertook historical research, documentation, and evaluation of the cultural heritage value or interest (under O.Reg.9/06) of an 1882 general store and residential building in the historic hamlet of Vandorf, Ontario. Assessed potential project-related impacts on heritage attributes and surrounding cultural heritage resources and recommended mitigation measures to lessen or avoid impacts.

Public Archaeology Excavation, Pinhey's Point Historic Site, Ottawa, Ontario - Field Assistance for public excavation of an agricultural outbuilding at Pinhey's Point Historic Site (Horaceville), the estate and mill complex established by Hamnett Pinhey in the 1820s. (Excavation directed by National Capital Commission and City of Ottawa).

Cultural Heritage Resource Impact Assessment, 665 Woolwich Street, Guelph, Ontario – Undertook historical research, documentation, and evaluation of the cultural heritage value or interest (under O.Reg.9/06) of a circa 1906 residence and barn. Assessed potential project-related impacts on cultural heritage resources and recommended mitigation measures to lessen or avoid impacts.

Historical Research, Environmental Assessment, Wolfe Island Ferry, Kingston, Ontario and Township of Frontenac Islands, Ontario – Undertook historical research and prepared background history document for the Kingston and Wolfe Island terminals of the Wolfe Island Ferry.

Cultural Heritage Landscape Strategy
Implementation, Phase 1, Oakville, Ontario –
Researching, documenting and evaluating
approximately 50 cultural heritage landscapes in
order to provide the Town of Oakville with an
inventory of cultural heritage landscapes and
prioritized recommendations for conservation.

Seaton Cultural Heritage Property Evaluations, Pickering, Ontario – Researching and preparing cultural heritage evaluations for ten properties along the Whitevale Road corridor for the City of Pickering.

Stage 2 Archaeological Assessment, Properties #27, 33 and 35 Scissons Road, Ottawa, Ontario - Field Technician and Peer Review of Report (work undertaken for Cameron Heritage Consulting) 2014

LeBreton Flats Archaeological Collection: Artifact Identification and Historical Research Project, Ottawa, Ontario – Prepared a historical overview paper and detailed catalogue records for the interpretation of a representative artifact collection from the 200,000 artifact LeBreton Flats Archaeological Collection. An overview podcast was also prepared, in French and English, as an interpretative tool for use by the city's museums group.

Heritage Registry Project: King Street to Chopin Drive, Cambridge, Ontario - Recorded and evaluated (per O.Reg.9/06 and Cambridge OP criteria) approximately 75 properties in a Preston neighbourhood for updates to the Heritage Register.

Heritage Impact Statement, 5175 Mississauga Road, Mississauga, Ontario - Recorded and evaluated (per O.Reg.9/06) residential building and surrounding environs to determine potential development impacts on cultural heritage resources.

Heritage Impact Statement, 5215 Mississauga Road, Mississauga, Ontario - Recorded and evaluated (per O.Reg.9/06) residential building and surrounding environs to determine potential development impacts on cultural heritage resources.

Heritage Impact Assessment, 11742 Tenth Line, Stouffville, Ontario - Recorded and evaluated (per O.Reg.9/06) residential building and surrounding environs to determine potential development impacts on cultural heritage resources.

Heritage Impact Assessment, 2409-2411 Lake Shore Blvd. W., Etobicoke, Ontario - Recorded and evaluated (per O.Reg.9/06) residential building and surrounding environs to determine potential development impacts on cultural heritage resources.

Stages 1 and 2 Archaeological Assessment, 2409-11 Lake Shore Blvd. W., Etobicoke, Ontario Archaeological investigations of a residential property under the 2011 Standards and Guidelines for Consultant Archaeologists.

Burritt's Rapids Heritage Conservation District Study, Burritt's Rapids, Ontario (Masters Candidate, 2010)

# Christienne Uchiyama, M.A.

Heritage Consultant and Archaeologist

Selected projects while at Stantec Consulting Ltd. 2010-2013

Review of Provincial and Territorial Policy, Legislation and Grey Literature Concerning Heritage Impact Assessment for the Canadian Environmental Assessment Agency, Ottawa, Ontario (2013)

Documentation of 41 Heritage Built Heritage Resources, Weber Street Class EA, Kitchener, Ontario (Heritage Planning Consultant and Lead Report Author, 2012-2013)

Heritage Impact Assessment, Victoria Park Lake Rehabilitation, Kitchener, Ontario (Heritage Planning Consultant, 2011-2012)

Heritage Impact Assessment, Genesis Pipeline Extension Project, Corunna, Ontario (Heritage Planning Consultant, 2011)

Heritage Impact Assessment, Almonte Solar Project, Mississippi Mills, Ontario (Heritage Planning Consultant, 2011)

Cultural Heritage Evaluation and Impact Assessment, Matheson Hydro Service Centre, Matheson, Ontario (2010)

Cultural Heritage Evaluation Report, Picton Hydro Service Centre, Picton, Ontario (2010)

Heritage Impact Assessment, Weber Street Class EA, Kitchener, Ontario (Heritage Planning Consultant and Report Author, 2010-2011)

Cultural Heritage Impact Statement, 435 Gladstone Avenue, Ottawa, Ontario (Heritage Planning Consultant, 2011)

Cultural Heritage Assessment, Conlin Road West, Class EA, Oshawa, Ontario (Heritage Planning Consultant, 2010)

Built Heritage and Cultural Heritage Landscape Assessment, Chelmsford By-Pass, Chelmsford, Ontario (Heritage Planning Consultant, 2010)

Cultural Heritage Evaluation Reports, CPR and Hazley Bay Bridges, Hwy 148, Pembroke, Ontario (Heritage Planning Consultant, 2010)

Selected projects while at Jacques Whitford Environment Ltd.

Built Heritage Assessment, Proposed New East-West Road corridor (Highway 6 to Brant Street), Hamilton, Ontario (2009)

Built Heritage Assessment, Waterdown Road Corridor, Hamilton, Ontario (2009)

## SELECTED PAPERS AND PRESENTATIONS

Heritage Hoarders? Archaeological Cultural Heritage Resources in Ontario, Paper presented at the Carleton University Heritage Conservation Symposium, 2015

Heritage in Environmental Assessment, Presentation Heritage Canada Foundation National Summit, 2012

Heritage Conservation Education: A Recent Graduate's Perspective, National Roundtable on Heritage Education, 2012

Waste of Place: Heritage Conservation within the Context of the Canadian Environmental Assessment Act. Masters Thesis, 2012

Waste of Place: Heritage Conservation and Environmental Assessment. Presentation and Paper. Carleton University Heritage Conservation Symposium, 2012

### AWARDS AND HONOURS

Carleton University Design Charette, Chaudière Island, Ottawa, Ontario (2012) – Martin Weaver Scholarship recipient for second place project

Ottawa Women's Canadian Club Scholarship (2011-12)

ICOMOS Canada Design Charette Adaptive Reuse of Building 50, Ottawa, Ontario (Masters Candidate, 2011) – Martin Weaver Scholarship recipient for first place project

North Grenville Heritage Award (2010) for Adaptive Re-Use Case Study of Six Heritage Buildings in North Grenville, Kemptville, Ontario (Masters Candidate, 2009)